Guide to the Agricultural Experiment Station oral histories, 1962-1965.
Agricultural Experiment Station oral histories
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Agricultural Experiment Station oral histories, 1962-1965.
13-6-944
New York State Agricultural Experiment Station.
Tape recordings and 1389 pages of transcript.
Audio tapes and transcripts of interviews.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Tapes and transcripts of oral history interviews by Gould P. Colman with Paul J. Chapman, Arthur C. Dahlberg, Robert E. Doran, Arthur J. Heinicke, George J. Hucker, James D. Luckett, Carl S. Pederson, Charles B. Sayre, Jessie E. Sperry, Donald K. Tressler, and Richard Wellington.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The New York State Agricultural Experiment Station at Geneva, New York is a unit of the New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences at Cornell University,Ithaca, New York.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Tapes and transcripts of oral history interviews by Gould P. Colman with Paul J. Chapman, Arthur C. Dahlberg, Robert E. Doran, Arthur J. Heinicke, George J. Hucker, James D. Luckett, Carl S. Pederson, Charles B. Sayre, Jessie E. Sperry, Donald K. Tressler, and Richard Wellington.
These interviews cover the research, administration, and public service contributions of the New York State Agricultural Experiment Station. Scientists, administrators, support staff, and other Geneva residents were interviewed. Topics include: relationships of Geneva faculty and staff with their Ithaca campus counterparts, including coordination of research and administration on the 2 campuses, and with New York State farmers and agricultural organizations, especially the food processing industry; relationships of Geneva station with other American agricultural experiment stations; and research by Geneva scientists in entomology (including the use of pesticides and biological control), vegetable crops, viticulture, pomology, bacteriology, food science, and dairy science (including the transfer to dairy research to the Ithaca campus).
Also, development of Geneva physical facilities, especially after WWII and during the 1960's; Geneva publications; administration of substations in the Hudson Valley and Fredonia; procurement of funds; hiring and promotion of staff and administrators; conducting seed investigations in coordination with the New York State Department of Agriculture and Markets; influence of personality on Cornell's agricultural research and teaching; assessment of Cornell administrators; participation by Geneva staff in community activities. Personal histories are also included.
SUBJECTS
Names:
New York State Agricultural Experiment Station.; Adams, Morton 1910-; Anderson, Rudolph John, 1879-; Babcock, H. E. (Howard Edward), 1889-1950.; Barton, Donald W., 1921-; Becker, Robert F.; Birdseye, Clarence; Brady, Nyle C.; Breed, Robert S. (Robert Stanley), 1877-1956.; Call, David L.; Carey, Hugh L.; Chandler, William Henry, 1878-; Chapman, P. J. (Paul Jones), 1900-; Chapman, Paul J.; Clark, Benjamin E., 1914-1983; Colman, Gould P. (Gould Patchin), 1926-; Connaway, John W.; Cook, Constance E.; Crosby, Cyrus R., 1879-1937.; Dahlberg, Arthur Chester.; Dahlberg, Arthur, 1896-1964; Dalrymple, Daniel M.; Daniel, Derrill McCollough, 1905-; Davis, Alexander C.; Doran, Robert E.; Downing, Donald L.; Dyson, John, active 1797; Eckles, Clarence Henry, 1875-; Einset, John, 1915-; Frank, Konstantin, 1899-1972.; Frommer, Charles; Gilmer, Robert M.; Glass, Edward H.; Greig, Robert G., 1913-; Hall, Frank Henry, 1866-1929; Hamilton, James M.; Hand, David B.; Hedrick, U. P.; Heinicke, Arthur J.; Heinicke, Arthur J., 1892-1971; Hofer, Alvin W.; Holland, Robert F.; Hucker, George J., 1893-1988; Hunter, James E.; Hurd, Thomas Norman, 1910; Jordan, Whitman Howard, 1851-; Kender, Walter J.; Kennedy, Wilbert Keith, 1919-; King, Joseph P.; Krauss, R. E. (Roscoe E.); Krauss, Roscoe E.; Lehman, Herbert H., (Herbert Henry), 1878-1963.; Luckett, James D., 1891-1968; Mann, Albert Russell, 1880-1947.; Massey, Louis Melville, 1889-1969.; McEwen, Freeman Lester, 1926-; McNew, George.; Morrison, F. B. (Frank Barron), 1887-1958; Palm, Charles Edmund, 1911-1996; Parrot, Percival John, 1874-1953; Pederson, Carl S., 1897-1987; Pederson, Charles S.; Porter, Gilbert; Robinson, Willard; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Sayre, Charles Bovett, 189l.-; Sayre, Charles Bovett.; Sherman, William.; Smith, George A.; Sperry, Jessie E.; Stewart, Fred Carlton, 1868-1940; Taylor, Walter S.; Thatcher, Roscoe Wilfred, 1872-; Tressler, Donald Kiteley, 1894-; Tukey, H. B.; Tyler, Winfield.; Van Slyke, Lucius Lincoln, 1859-; VanDemark, Noland L.; Vittum, Morrill T.; Wellington, R. (Richard); Wellington, Richard, 1884-1975; Whitten, John C. 1866-; Wickham, Don J., 1903-; Agricultural Research Planning and Coordination.; Associated Food Processors.; Cornell University. Office of Vice President for Land Grant Affairs.; Cornell University. Cooperative Extension.; New Jersey, New York, Pennsylvania Agricultural Research Coordination.; New York (State). Pesticide Control Board.; New York (State). Department of Environmental Conservation; New York (State). Pesticide Control Board; New York State Agricultural Experiment Station. Department of Entomology.; New York State Agricultural Experiment Station. Department of Food Science and Technology.; New York State Agricultural Experiment Station. Department of Pomology and Viticulture.; New York State Agricultural Experiment Station. Department of Seed and Vegetable Sciences.; New York State Agricultural Experiment Station. Department of Plant Pathology.; New York State Agricultural Experiment Station. Department of Publications.; New York State Agricultural Experiment Station. Hudson Valley Laboratory (Highland, N.Y.); New York State Agricultural Experiment Station. Vineyard Laboratory (Fredonia, N.Y.); New York State Agricultural Experiment Station. Department of Buildings and Properties.; New York State Canners and Freezers Association.; New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences -- Administration.; New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences; New York State Fruit Testing Cooperative Association.; State University of New York.; University of Missouri.; Western New York Apple Growers Association.; Western New York Cherry Growers Association.
Titles:
Farm research.
Subjects:
Agriculture -- Research.; Agricultural chemicals -- Law and legislation.; Agricultural chemicals -- Environmental aspects.; Agricultural experiment stations.; Agricultural administration.; Viticulture.; Pesticides -- Environmental aspects.; Interdisciplinary approach in education.; Food industry and trade -- New York (State); DDT (Insecticide); Agricultural pests.; Pests -- Biological control.; Community and college -- New York (State) -- Geneva.; Pesticides -- Environmental aspects.; Dairying -- Research.; Fruit-culture -- New York (State); Food -- Bacteriology.; Voluntarism.; Agriculture publishing.; Food, Frozen.; Vegetables -- New York (State); Plant-breeding -- New York (State); Agricultural administration; Agricultural chemicals -- Law and legislation; Agricultural experiment stations; Community and college; Food industry and trade; Frozen foods; Fruit-culture; Management; Plant breeding; Vegetables
Places:
Geneva (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; New York (State); New York (State) -- Geneva
Form and Genre Terms:
Oral histories.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Related collection: New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences. Historical Documentation Program Oral Histories, #13-6-2082. Donald W. Barton, tr., trsc. 4912-4917, trsc. 5246-5248; Robert F. Becker, tr., trsc. 3852; Roscoe E. Krauss, trsc. 5325; Edward H. Smith tr., trsc. 4906-4911.
Related collection: New York State Food Processing Industry Oral History Project, #2378. Walter D. Enzie, trsc. 1210.
Related collection: Paul J. Chapman Papers, #22-1-2102
Related collection: Charles B. Sayre Seminar Transcript, # 22-1-m.1061.
Related collection: Richard Wellington Papers, #22-2-3558.
NOTES
Some of the 1962-1965 tapes have been erased; only 5 minute excerpts remain.
Also forms part of the Eastern Wine and Grape Archive. (EWGA)
CONTAINER LIST
- Chapman, Paul J., 1900-1993, Transcript #3888
  Occupation: Professor, editor, librarian
  See also collection #: 22-1-2102
  Recorded: November 5, 1964; February 8, 1965; March 5, 1965; April 12, 1965; and May 17, 1965
  Childhood botanical interest; graduate study and work with Spray Information Service at Cornell; experiences as an entomologist, 1930-1965, and as head of Dept. of Entomology, Geneva, 1948-1965, esp. work at Hudson Valley substation; selection of research projects; research methods; spray residue control problems; biological controls; relationships of department with other departments at the Station; relations of Station with Cornell, NY State Dept. of Agriculture and Markets, USDA, growers, the Geneva community, industry; administration of dept., esp. selection of personnel; comments concerning faculty status, esp. tenure, sabbatic leave; recollections concerning Cyrus Crosby, P. J. Parrott, L. M. Massey, D. M. Daniels, A. J. Heinicke, Alvin Hoefer, George McNew, Harold Tukey.
- Dahlberg, Arthur Chester, 1896-1964, Transcript #3889
  Occupation: Professor of Dairy Science
  Recorded: November 12, 1962; February 22, 1963
  Development of the work in dairy chemistry at the New York State Agricultural Experiment Station at Geneva; descriptions of major research projects; reflections concerning George A. Smith, R. W. Thatcher, F. B. Morrison, and G. P. Hedrick; removal of dairy work to Ithaca.
- Doran, Robert E., 1899-1983, Transcript #3890
  Occupation: Geneva physician
  Recorded: March 27, 1963
  Participation of staff on Geneva in political and social organizations in Geneva, NY.
- Heinicke, Arthur J., 1892-1971, Transcript #3891
  Cornell Class: Ph.D. 1916
  Occupation: Professor, pomology/Director
  Recorded: November 27, 1963; February 10, 1964; April 13, 1964; June 22, 1964; and September 16, 1964
  Agriculture in the St. Louis area, c. 1900; high school education; experiences at the University of Missouri; impressions of J. W. Connaway, J. C. Whitten, C. H. Eckles, W. H. Chandler, others; facilities for research, research methods and objectives in Dept. of Pomology at Cornell, c. 1914; relationships between research in orchard soils, spraying practice, pruning practices, and apple varieties; relation of work in pomology at Cornell to that of New York State Agricultural Experiment Station, 1942-1960; comment concerning Geneva including appointment as director, postwar building program, elimination of dairy herd, beginning of Dept. of Food Science and Technology, establishment of systematic budget procedures, methods for coordinating work with NYS College of Agriculture; impressions of Herbert Lehman, U. P. Hedrick, P. J. Parrott.
- Hucker, George J., 1893-1988, Transcript #1204
  Occupation: Professor of Bacteriology
  Also part of the Food Processing Oral History Project, #237
  Recorded: November 2, 1962; November 9, 1962; November 30, 1962; December 4, 1962; January 22, 1963; February 20, 1963; March 27, 1963; April 23, 1963; May 6, 1963; May 20, 1963; and June 10, 1963
  Work in bacteriology at New York State Agricultural Experiment Station at Geneva; reminiscences and reflections concerning Directors W. H. Jordan, R. W. Thatcher, F. B. Morrison, U. P. Hedrick, P. J. Parrott, and A. J. Heinicke, and Professors R. S. Breed, F. C. Stewart, D. W. Carpenter, George Smith, L. L. Van Slyke, Rudolph Anderson, H. B. Tukey, J. D. Luckett, A. W. Hofer, also A. R. Mann and H. E. Babcock; Station procedures; relationships of the staff to administration and to the Geneva community; development of Dept. of Food Science and Technology; establishment of Food Research, relationship of Station to canning and freezing industry. 8.
- Luckett, James D., 1891-1968, Transcript #3892
  Occupation: Editor/Librarian
  Recorded: October 8, 1962.
  Development of extension work at the New York State Agricultural Experiment Station at Geneva; reminiscences concerning the Station staff, esp. W. H. Jordan, R. W. Thatcher, U. P. Hedrick, A. J. Heinicke.
- Pederson, Carl S., 1897-1987, Transcript #3893
  Cornell Class: Ph.D 1929
  Occupation: Professor, bacteriology
  Recorded: October 15, 1962; November 19, 1962
  Development of work in bacteriology at the New York State Agricultural Experiment Station at Geneva; reminiscences concerning R. W. Thatcher, F. B. Morrison, U. P. Hedrick, R. S. Breed, Donald Tressler; relationship of Station staff to food industry and to Geneva community.
- Sayre, Charles Bovett, 1891-1979, Transcript #3894
  Occupation: Professor, vegetable crops
  See also collection #: 22-1-m.1061
  Recorded: November 9, 1962
  Work in vegetable crops at Geneva; major research projects; recollections concerning Frank Hall, U. P. Hedrick, P. J. Parrott, and A. J. Heinicke, 1925-1960.
- Sperry, Jessie E., 1888-1968, Transcript #3895
  Occupation: Secretary to Director
  Recorded: November 30, 1962
  Recollections concerning the administrative procedures and staff at New York State Agricultural Experiment Station at Geneva; Directors W. H. Jordan, R. W. Thatcher, F. B. Morrison, U. P. Hedrick, P. J. Parrott, and A. J. Heinicke, and Professors L. L. Van Slyke, F. C. Stewart, J. D. Luckett, Frank Hall.
- Tressler, Donald Kiteley, 1894-1981, Transcript #1198
  Occupation: Chemist
  Also part of Food Processing Oral History Project, #2378
  Recorded: May 7, 1963; November 19, 1963
  High school and college education; utilization of food processing by-products; association with Clarence Birdseye; establishment of food freezing work at Geneva; analysis of food freezing industry prior to 1930; Birdseye’s innovations in packing and promoting frozen foods; development of work in food freezing at Geneva, esp. physical facilities, relationships between staff, graduate assistants, selection of research problems, research grants, administrative methods; New York State interest in food freezing; development of Food Research.
- Wellington, R. (Richard), 1884-1975, Transcript #3896
  Occupation: Professor of Pomology
  See also collection #: 22-2-3558
  Recorded: August 6, 1962, August 21, 1962
  Development of the work in pomology at Geneva; organization and activities of the New York State Fruit Testing Association; administration of the Station, esp. under W. H. Jordan and U. P. Hedrick, 1906-1960.